there's no fancy tub this week due to a
really needy eight-month-old baby
so this week we're going to talk about
the science of rocky road
[Music]
so when i was in america i went to one
of the wits frozen
custard outlets and tried their rocky
road and it was
incredible really really good it went
straight on my list of ice creams to try
and that is what we're gonna do today
we're gonna have a look and see if we
can recreate based on their ingredients
their ice cream but first
what is it what is rocky road
so there's no solid evidence online
surprise surprise
as to the actual origins of rocky road
but the information i can find is that
originated in australia in the mid-1800s
and it was developed
for one reason really and that was to
make sure that
that all the produce that's being varied
around the country
wasn't wasted they added chocolate
usually cheap chocolate
to the partially spoiled confection that
they were carrying
and that enabled them to create what was
then the rocky road
slab it was made as a sheet cake kind of
thing
chopped up into squares kind of like
brownies and sold like that
in the early 1900s it was brought over
to the uk
we sold it as tiffin back then but now
we're starting to sell it as rocky road
because england wants to be basically
anyone other than england
so we just copy everyone else's stuff
we're now
gonna move on to the rocky road ice
cream and this is kind of what is the
famous
part of the name there are claims that
the rocky road ice cream
was invented by fenton's creamery
i think that's california in the early
1900s but then there are other claims
that drea's ice cream holdings created
this flavor in 1929
who knows so what exactly
is rocky road
[Music]
so in australia it looks like this and
is
originally made with chocolate
marshmallows
cherries coconut and nuts
in the uk it's actually quite similar
but without the coconut
and tiffin has bits of biscuit in it as
well
in the u.s it's very rarely sold like
that it's really just sold as their ice
cream flavor
and that brings us on to wits now they
were kind enough to put their
ingredients and nutritional facts online
i'm going to put those here what we can
see is that it's a 17
fat 19 sugar which is quite high
but it's also got seven percent protein
which is also quite high so
let's see what we can do and try and
reverse engineer their rocky road
what we can actually do is break these
nutritional facts and ingredients down
using an ice cream calculator
here you can see me inputting different
numbers of
relevant ingredients to try and create
something around the 17
19 and 7 that we know which
has so with these basic numbers in place
we can actually get pretty close to this
but if you look down the bottom of the
ingredients list you'll see
a whole load of stabilizers and
that tetra sodium pyrophosphate
now that might sound like something you
really don't want to eat but in reality
it's just a type of salt salt has really
good freezing point depression ability
so will help with that ever attainable
scoop ability
all of these stabilizers are actually
vegan i know a lot of people don't like
using these
but in reality they're all made from
natural ingredients
such as seaweed now we've got all the
ingredients
we know what we're doing we're going to
suit up and get making
now one of the beautiful things about
making rocky road is there are so many
variations of this around the world
and because we had leftover chocolate
covered almonds from our serendipity ice
cream i'll put a link up in the corner
for you
we're going to use those and along with
our mini marshmallows and a little bit
extra of chopped milk
chocolate that will make this chocolate
base even better
a really easy base to make just put all
your ingredients in a pan
add those egg yolks heat it up to 80 to
85 degrees seed that will cook your egg
yolks without scrambling them
take it off the heat put it in a
container in your fridge for at least
four hours
so once your ice cream is properly
chilled you can pop it in your ice cream
machine to churn
that will take somewhere around 15 to 30
minutes depending on your machine
whilst your ice cream is churning you
can chop up your
almonds get your marshmallows ready chop
up your chocolate basically do whatever
you want to do with the stuff that
you're adding in
free rain when your ice cream is ready
then start loading it into your tub and
just layer in
all these ingredients you've got ready
whatever you like
go to town pop it in the freezer
for three to four hours until you're
ready to eat it
that's how you make rocky road let's go
and grab it out the freezer and see what
it looks like
there we go great scoop lovely and soft
you can see those almonds in there i
mean chocolate covered almonds you know
it's what we've got and
you just splash out and use what's in
your cupboard little mini marshmallows
little bits of chopped chocolate it's
looking good
let's just see what it's like
[Music]
it's really good it's a great flavor
it's a classic flavor rocky road
there's a weird thing in this the high
protein
but why that's in here i'm not quite
sure
they've actually made a conscious effort
to add additional
whey which is if you're not selling an
ice cream as a protein
based ice cream then kind of makes you
wonder why they do it
but it's got a good texture the strength
of the
chocolate flavor in the base is not too
overpowering and sometimes you get that
where it's a really punchy chocolate ice
cream you don't taste all the add-ins
you kind of want the add-ins to be the
point of this ice cream
the marshmallows go lovely and chewy in
the freezer now some marshmallows don't
go chewy some go rock hard
why they're all different i don't know
essentially it's to do with the sugar
content
the little chopped chocolate in there
just adds a little bit more
decadence to it just a little bit not
too much
i mean this is a great flavor rocky road
is a classic everyone likes rocky road
unless you hate chocolate then
you know this video isn't for you the
stabilizers in this
what do they do i mean they do different
things depending on
what stabilizer you use but essentially
they help the
fats bond to the water and create less
iciness
or they slow down the melting element or
they change the freezing point
depression
different ones do different things
normally you use a combination of both
now i can tell from their ingredients
they've actually probably used a
proprietary mix that they bought off the
shelf
it's quite common you can buy these
basically anywhere
and would you want to do that at home
if you make a big batch of it you want
to keep it in the freezer absolutely it
will last for months if you do this
if you don't add a kind of stabilizer or
any stabilizer
the ice cream will deteriorate over the
course of you know three to four weeks
but
in my house it doesn't last three or
four days so i don't normally use it
unless i make a big batch of something
and then i will
so there we have it a basic slightly
scientific breakdown of rocky road
is this the kind of video that you like
that scientific-ish element to ice cream
or would you just rather watch me make
loads of different flavors is there a
specific flavor that you want to see me
make
hit us down in the comments below let us
know and we'll see what we can do
but for now thanks very much for
watching don't forget to like and
subscribe and we'll see you next week
[Music]
you